John Brick Papers
John Brick Papers
1948 (ca)-1965
Brick, John.
5.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist, author (1922-1973). Correspondence, primarily in connection with the Author's Guild; manuscript novels and stories; galley proofs; photographs, and printed material, including articles and newspaper clippings by and about Brick. Manuscripts for novels Borne on the wind, Panther Mountain, Richmond Raid, Rogue's Kingdom, The Strong Men, and The Tyger.
148865
Biographical History
John Brick (1922-1973) was an American author of historical novels and children's books. Born in Newburgh, New York he attended Newburgh Free Academy and later studied creative writing at Columbia University.
His first published novel was Troubled Spring in 1950; other works include The Raid (1951), Homer Crist (1952), The Rifleman (1953), and Jubilee (1956). In addition to his writing, Brick was managing editor of Export Trade (1945-49), a staff writer for Life magazine (1960-61), assistant to the president of University of Toledo, Ohio (1962-63), and a professional staff member of United States Senate Permanent Investigations Subcommittee (from 1963).
John Brick was a member of the Authors Guild, P.E.N., and the Authors League.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Brick Papers consist of incoming and outgoing correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material.
Incoming correspondence and Outgoing correspondence consist of letters to Brick or written by him, respectively, and includes that of both individuals and organizations.
Subject files include book jackets, bulletins, business transactions, certificates, lists, notes, photographs, and so on.
Manuscripts contains original and typescript copies of novels and stories, as well as one speech.
Published material contains printed matter: galley proofs of some of Brick's books, magazine articles by and about him, newspaper clippings by and about him, and reviews of his books.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender; outgoing is arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type and then, if applicable, by title.
One box (Box 12) was added to the collection in 1967 but has not been physically integrated into it.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Brick, John, 1922-; Borne on the wind.; Panther mountain.; Richmond raid.; Rogue's kingdom.; Strong men.; Tyger.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Incoming correspondence
  - A - W, 1962-1966 (Box 12)
  - A (Box 1)
  - Authors Guild (Box 1)
  - B (Box 1)
  - Breslin, Howard and Pat (Box 1)
  - C (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - Donadio, Candida (Box 1)
  - Doubleday and Company, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Doubleday and Company, Inc., 1964; 1965 (Box 12)
  - E (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Mrs. Margaret (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Straus, Young & Company, Inc. (Box 1)
  - G (Box 2)
  - H (Box 2)
  - Hart, Moss (Authors Guild) (Box 2)
  - Hatfield, Ernest I. (Box 2)
  - Heggie, Peter (Authors Guild) (Box 2)
  - Hersey, John (Authors Guild) (Box 2)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar (Box 2)
  - J (Box 2)
  - K (Box 2)
  - Kelly, Michael (Box 2)
  - Kerr, Lowell (Box 2)
  - L (Box 2)
  - M (Box 2)
  - McIntosh, Mavis, 1964; 1965,; undated (Box 12)
  - McIntosh, Mavis and McKee, Elizabeth (literary representatives) (Box 2)
  - Miller, Merle (Authors Guild) (Box 2)
  - N - O (Box 2)
  - P (Box 2)
  - Pearce, Charles A. (Deull, Sloan and Pearce, Inc.), 1961; 1962,; 1964 (Box 12)
  - Pearce, Charles A. (Deull, Sloan and Pearce, Inc.) (Box 2)
  - G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1963; 1965 (Box 12)
  - R (Box 2)
  - Roulston, Margaret Hillis (Authors Guild) (Box 2)
  - S (Box 3)
  - Shirer, William L. (Authors League) (Box 3)
  - Sillicox, Luise (Authors League) (Box 3)
  - Stephens, Willis H. (Box 3)
  - Stout, Rex (Box 3)
  - T - V (Box 3)
  - W (Box 3)
  - Wouk, Herman (Authors League) (Box 3)
  - Y - Z (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
- Outgoing correspondence
  - 11 Oct 1948 - 20 Sep 1963 (Box 3)
  - 1954, 1962-1964 (Box 12)
- Subject files
  - Author's Guild Bulletin (Box 4)
  - Author's Guild and P.E.N. material (Box 4)
  - Book jackets (Box 4)
  - Business transactions (Box 4)
  - Certificates, membership cards, permits (Box 4)
  - Grade reports from Columbia University (Box 4)
  - Lists - membership (Box 4)
  - Matrix (Box 4)
  - Mid-Hudson School Board Institute (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Notes (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Brick (Box 4)
  - Pornography material, on censorship, ACLU, etc (Box 4)
  - Synopsis of Brick's books (Box 4)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - Ben Bryan, Morgan Rifleman (Box 4)
    - Borne on the Wind, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Captives of the Seneca (Box 5)
    - On the Old Frontier, 1966; 2 copies (Box 12)
    - Panther Mountain, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Richmond Raid, pp. 1-230 (Box 5)
    - Richmond Raid, pp. 231-459 (Box 6)
    - Rogue's Kingdom, pp. 1-260; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Rogue's Kingdom, pp. 261-590; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - The Strong Men, pp. 1-420; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - The Strong Men, pp. 421-555 (Box 8)
    - The Tyger, 6 folders (Box 8)
    - We Band of Brothers (incomplete) (Box 8)
  - Book jacket flaps - The Strong Men (Box 8)
  - Poems by others (Box 8)
  - Speech at NYSSBA Shared Services Conference (Box 8)
  - Stories
    - "Council for the Defense" (Box 8)
    - "Down on Front Street" (Box 8)
    - "No Evidence" (Box 8)
    - "Fire on the Mountain", 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "The Hunter" (Box 9)
    - "A Message for Uncle Billy" (Box 9)
    - "Sailor" (Box 9)
    - "The Spikehorn Buck" (Box 9)
    - "There was a Man" (Box 9)
  - Synopsis of various Brick books (Box 9)
- Published material
  - Galley proofs
    - Ben Bryan, Morgan Rifleman, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Captives of the Seneca, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Richmond Raid (Box 9)
    - The Richmond Raid, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Rogue's Kingdom (Box 10)
    - Rogue's Kingdom, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Magazine articles
    - About Brick (Box 11)
    - By Brick, "Rally for Reprints" (Box 11)
    - Book synopses (Box 11)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About Brick (Box 11)
    - About Brick, 1961 (Box 12)
    - By Brick (Box 11)
    - Book reviews (Box 11)
    - Book reviews, 1963-1965 (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11)